Suma Gowrishankar

(510) 402-9384 | sumagowrishankar@gmail.com | Mountain House, CA | Github Repository: https://github.com/sumags-1 LinkedIn: https://www.linkedin.com/in/sumagowrishankar/

SOFTWARE ENGINEER

Software Engineer with a background in Quality Assurance and Product Design, over the last 20 plus years. Having been on both sides of the software development process thus far has given me a unique perspective to visualize and strive to write clear and concise code that delivers on quality within deadlines.

I have primarily worked in the Identity Protection services and Credit Services industry and am skilled in Web development, particularly HTML CSS JavaScript and ReactJS, as well as Product Management, Requirements definition, Test Management, Test planning and coordination.

SKILLS

LANGUAGES: HTML5, CSS3, EJS, JavaScript, ReactJS, NodeJS, Express, Python, Mongoose, Django

DATABASES: MongoDB, PostgreSQL, mySQL, Oracle

CSS FRAMEWORKS: Bootstrap, Materialize, TailwindCSS

PROFICIENCIES: MERN stack, Problem Solving, Strategic Planning, Agile Scrum Team, GitHub, Web API, Data Analysis, Front-End Web Development, Full-Stack Web Development, Requirements Gathering, Test Planning and Execution, Defect Management and reporting, Preparation of User Guides, Product walk through for clients, Certified SAFE Agilist and PO/PM

TOOLS: Postman for API testing, Github for version control, Aha for Project Management, JIRA for Agile planning, tracking and Bugzilla for defect tracking

RECENT PROJECTS

New Beginnings, the Crystal Shop - https://new-beginnings-app.herokuapp.com/

- MERN stack (Mongoose, Express, React, Node) app with full CRUD for authenticated and authorized users
- Role based execution of full CRUD only admin roles can access certain features while visitors can only browse the site and save to wishlist
- Used Tailwind CSS with React to render views
- Used Git throughout the process for version control; tested features before implementing

Library Page Turners - https://library-page-turners.herokuapp.com/

- MEN stack app (Mongoose, EJS, Express and Node.js)
- Used HTML5, CSS3, Bootstrap, EJS and Javascript to create views of Library app
- Implemented authentication with sign up / log in / log out functions using JWT
- Built the app with full CRUD functionality on two models using Javascript on Node.js and Express frameworks; data stored on MongoDB and accessed through Mongoose

Hikers Hub - https://hikers-hub.herokuapp.com/

- Created wireframes for the project using Figma, and user stories with Trello
- Group project, worked with 3 others to create this MERN (Mongoose, Express, React and Node) stack app with full CRUD for authorized users
- Implemented authentication functionality for users to signup/login/logout with JWT
- Used Bootstrap with React to render views
- Implemented third party integration of Weather API

PROFESSIONAL EXPERIENCE

iCompaas

Product Manager: 2021

- Freelance short term project for a startup, working on the flagship product as well as a Document management system product
- Provided first point of contact for prospective clients that wanted to try out the product, acknowledged and addressed needs that translated into Requirements for the teams
- Mentored product team in India and handed off the role to them

Equifax Inc and TrustedID Inc (acquired by Equifax Inc): 2008 to 2020

Quality Assurance Analyst from 2008-2013

Quality Assurance Manager from 2013-2020 (last 2 years had combined responsibility)

Product Owner from 2018 to 2020

- Piloted the Quality assurance process besides working on new products and project releases
- Prepared high-level conditions, test cases and managed traceability of requirements, as well as test
 environments, and managed defect cycles for System testing and User Acceptance Testing.
- Prepared and reviewed Test Scenarios with the Product team that served as requirements for Engineering, design and development efforts.
- Contributed to design discussions with the Engineering team.
- Co-ordinated change control, User Acceptance testing with the Product team and managed its defect cycle.
- Authored User guides for customer support tools and end clients.
- Conducted final product walk-through to Customer support and end client as required
- Moved to Lead Product Owner role in 2018 after demonstrating subject matter expertise to Business Product Management and Engineering team alike on Identity Theft Protection domain.
- Handled combined responsibilities of Product Owner and Quality Assurance Manager to manage product requirements and quality assurance deliverables respectively.
- Managed a team of 6 QA personnel, both full time as well as contractors. Mentored interns every year and converted two into full time QA Engineers.
- Delivered numerous projects, including Lock and Alert, web and mobile product, to instantly lock and unlock Equifax consumer credit reports, TrustedID Premier product, a complete credit report and alert product created in the event of the Equifax Data breach in 2017, integration of TrustedID products with Equifax Credit Services. TrustedID products were offered through partner channels such as LifeLock, Credit Karma, Mint.com, AARP, H&R Block, and maintenance and enhancements of all organic products offered by TrustedID.

Thinksoft Global Services Pvt Ltd (contractor for Citibank Global): 1998 to 2006

Web Developer, Manual QA tester: Citibank India Technologies

Web Developer, Manual QA tester: Citibank Private Banking Group, Zurich QA Automation Engineer for Performance testing: Citibank Technologies, Spain

UAT Coordinator: Citibank Technologies, Germany

UAT Coordinator and Defect Manager: Citibank Technologies, Greece

- Prepared high-level conditions, test cases and managed traceability of requirements, as well as test
 environments, and managed defect cycles for System testing and User Acceptance Testing
- Managed a team of 13 test personnel while handling UAT coordinator duties

EDUCATION

General Assembly, Software Engineering, Jan 2023 (Web Development)

NIIT - Web Development (HTML, CSS, JAVA)

Software Solutions Integrated - Post Graduate Diploma in Computer Applications (C, C++, VB, Oracle)

University of Madras - Bachelor of Arts in Corporate Secretaryship